Intro to refactoring

1. Introduction

Focused more on how refactoring and unit testing is supported by tools currently available. By applying multiple iterations of refactoring on the program its design will improve considerably and new features will be easier to add.

2. What Is Refactoring?

2.1 Definition

Refactoring : A change made to the internal structure of software to make it easier to understand and cheaper to modify without changing its observable behavior.

2.2 Hitory

Although the methodology can be used with almost every programming language, object-oriented languages make things easier. This is specially ture for the more complex refactorings, which rely heavily on objects, inheritance and polymorphism.

2.3 Why Refactoring matters

About 50% of all programming effort in most enterpises goes into maintaining software. Refactoring will help to improve the design, make the code easier to understand and maintain.

3. Unit Testing

“Software features that can't be demonstrated by automated tests simply don exist”

It is not component testing, which is interested whether the application behaves generally the way it was specified it should. See for further information about the difference.

3.1 Why testing is important

Whether you like Extreme Programming or not, tests have been proven to be the methodology to ultimately control if the changes you just made to your code introduced bugs. Because refactoring is all about changing code, testing is a must.

3.2 The JUnit Framework

3.2.3 Assertions

assertEquals

assertFalse

assertNotNull

assertNotSame

assertNull

assertSame

assertTrue

fail

4. Refactoring a concrete example

4.1 The starting point

4.2 Comments of the program

Rule 1: When you find you have to add a feature to a program, and the program's code is not structured in a convenient way to add the feature, first refactor the program to make it easy to add the feature, then add the feature.

5. Steps in refactoring the concrete example

5.1 Creating Unit Tests

the goal is to keep the observable behavior of a program, even if we change its underlying structure. So a fundamental thing to have are solid tests.

Rule2 : Before you start refactoring, check that you have a solid suite of tests. These tests must be self-checking.

5.2 Decomposing the statement() method

6 Bad Smells in Code

Refactoring is centainly not(only) about aesthetics, about beautiful code - so a somewhat solid tem had to be found by Martin Fowler to describe when refactorign should be applied:

“If it stinks, change it”

6.1 Duplicated Code

6.2 Long Method and Large Class

6.3 Long Parameter List

Long parameter lists are hard to understand and usually deliver too much information to the method. With objects, you can always ask another object to get the needed information for you. Using Replace Parameter with Method may be a solution to separate a parameter logically from the others. Alternatively you could pass a special parameter object(a Value Object or Transfer Object)

6.4 Feature Envy

6.5 Data Clumps

It is frequent that the same set of variables are spotted together in various places of the code. Use Extract Class to group together those variables in their own class.

6.6 Speculative Generality

Sometimes you're implementing handling for special cases that are probably never used. The result are methods which are only called by their own tests and thus only add to the complexity of maintenance and understanding. Replace unnecessary delegation with the code of the delegate(Inline Class), Collapse the Hierarchy if there are abstract classes not doing much. Purge unused parameters, rename methods, fields and classes to achieve sensible names.

6.7 Temporary Field

Temporary variables can be replaced with the expression used to the set the variable(Inline Temp).

6.8 Message chains

If you have code like the following snippet, you should consider getting the target object directly

6.9 Inappropriate Intimacy

Some classes know too much about other classes and should therefore be broken up(use Move Method and Move Field, or extract common code into another class). Subclasses are an example for this misbehavior, because they always know too much about their parent. You can replace the inheritance with delegation in this case.

6.10 Comments

Rule 3 : When you feel the need to write a comment, first try to refactor the code so that any comment becomes superfluous.

7. Principles

7.1 Why should You Refactor?

The following points give you a broad overview why you should consider refactoring for your own projects. These points highlight the strengths of refactoring.

Improving the design of software

Refactoring makes software easier to understand

Refactoring helps you find bugs

Refactoring helps you program faster

7.2 When ?

Refactor when you add function : Adding features to code you don't fully understand is easier when you refactor.

Refactor when you need to fix a bug

Refactor as you do a code review

8 Problems

There are areas where you should take care that refactoring does not make things worse instead of better.

Database : Because application using databases are tightly coupled to the data model in the database, refactoring the application alone is not enough. Refactoring databases although is not easy if you have to do it by hand. A possible solution is an intermediate layer which takes care of persistence and can be refactor without problems.

Changing interfaces : It is disturbing that refactoring generally changes interfaces. If people rely on frozen interfaces you published, their code won't work anymore after you refactored them. To avoid this, you can arrange it that the old interface calls the new one(but don't copy-paste methods because of the resulting code duplication) and thus the old and new interfaces run in parallel. In Java, mark the old interface as deprecated.

There are situations when you shouldn't refactor. If for example the existing code base is just a mess, is full of bugs and does not work even rudimentary, you should consider a total rewrite. Another time refactoring should be avoided is when you are close to a deadline. The productivity gain would only appear after the deadline and thus be too late.

11 Conclusion

Chapter 06 기본 객체와 영역

05) JSP 기본 객체와 영역

웹 어플리케이션은 네 개의 영역(scope)을 갖고 있는데, 이들 영역은 다음과 같다.

PAGE 영역 - 하나의 JSP 페이지를 처리할 때 사용되는 영역

REQUEST 영역 - 하나의 HTTP 요청을 처리할 때 사용되는 영역

SESSION 영역 - 하나의 웹 브라우저와 관련된 영역

APPLICATION 영역 - 하나의 웹 어플리케이션과 관련된 영역

PAGE 영역은 한번의 클라이언트 요청에 대해서 하나의 JSP 페이지를 범위로 갖는다. 즉, 웹 브라우저의 요청이 들어오면 JSP 페이지를 실행하게 되는데, 이때 JSP 페이지를 실행하는 범위가 하나의 PAGE 영역이 된다.

REQUEST 영역은 웹 브라우저의 한번의 요청과 관련된다. 즉, 웹 브라우저의 주소에 URL을 입력하거나 또는 링크를 클릭해서 페이지를 이동할 때, 웹 브라우저가 웹 서버에 전송하는 요청이 하나의 REQUEST 영역이 된다. 웹 브라우저가 요청을 보낼 때마다 매번 새로운 REQUEST 영역이 생성된다. PAGE 영역과 차이점이 있다면, PAGE 영역은 오직 하나의 JSP 페이지만을 포함하는데 반해, REQUEST 영역은 하나의 요청을 처리하는데 사용되는 모든 JSP 페이지를 포함한다.

SESSION 영역은 하나의 웹 브라우저와 관련된 영역이다. 일단, 세션이 생성되면 하나의 웹 브라우저와 관련된 모든 요청은 하나의 SESSION 영역에 포함된다.

APPLICATION 영역은 하나의 웹 애플리케이션과 관련된 전체 영역을 포함한다. 예를 들어, 이 장에서 사용 중인 예제인 /chap06 웹 어플리케이션에 포함된 모든 요청과 브라우저의 세션은 모두 하나의 APPLICATION 영역에 속하게 된다.

06) JSP 기본 객체의 속성(Attribute) 사용하기

네 개의 기본 객체는 속성을 갖고 있다. 속성은 각각의 기본 객체가 존재하는 동안에 사용될 수 있으며, JSP 페이지 사이에서 정보를 주고 받거나 공유하기 위한 목적으로 사용된다.

6.1 속성의 값 타입

속성의 이름은 문자열을 나타내는 String 타입이지만, 값은 기본 데이터 타입을 제외한 나머지 모든 클래스 타입이 올 수 있다.

6.2 속성의 활용 방법

속성의 쓰임새

기본 객체 | 영역 | 쓰임새
pageContext | PAGE | (한번의 요청을 처리하는) 하나의 JSP 페이지 내에서 공유될 값을 저장한다. 주로 커스텀 태그에서 새로운 변수를 추가할 때 사용된다.
request | REQUEST | 한번의 요청을 처리하는데 사용되는 모든 JSP 페이지에서 공유될 값을 저장한다.
session | SESSION | 한 사용자와 관련된 정보를 JSP들이 공유하기 위해서 사용된다. 사용자의 로그인 정보와 같은 것들을 저장한다.
application | APPLICATION | 모든 사용자와 관련해서 공유할 정보를 저장한다. 임시 디렉터리 경로와같은 웹 어플리케이션의 설정 정보를 주로 저장한다.

1장 오브젝트와 의존관계

1.1 초난감 DAO

DAO : DB를 사용해 데이터를 조회하거나 조작하는 기능을 전담하도록 만든 오브젝트를 말한다.

1.1.1 User

JavaBean : 원래 비주얼 툴에서 조작 가능한 컴포넌트를 말한다. 자바의 주력 개발 플랫폼이 웹 기반의 엔터프라이 방식으로 바뀌면서 비주얼 컴포넌트로서의 자바빈은 인기를 잃어 갔지만 몇 가지 코딩 관례는 자바빈 스타일의 오브젝트를 사용하는 오픈소스 기술을 통해 계속 이어져 왔다. 다음 두 가지 관례를 따라 만들어진 오브젝트를 가리킨다.

디폴트 생성자 : 자바빈은 파라미터가 없는 디폴트 생성자를 갖고 있어야 한다. 툴이나 프레임워크에서 리플렉션을 이용해 오브젝트를 생성하기 때문에 필요하다.

프로퍼티 : 자바빈이 노출하는 이름을 가진 속성을 말한다. getter setter로 불리는 수정자/접근자 메서드를 통해 조회할 수 있다.

(참고)리플렉션 : 정의된 것을 찾는 행위로서 동적 언어의 특징이다. 클래스나 메서드는 컴파일 되어 메모리에 올라가 프로그램 입장에서는 그것을 호출하거나 사용할 수만 있는데 리플렉션을 지원하는 언어는 그것 뿐 아니라 아예 정의 자체를 찾아와 조작하는 기능까지 제공한다.

1.1.2 UserDao

1.1.3 main()을 이용한 DAO 테스트 코드

1.2 DAO의 분리

1.2.1 관심사의 분리

관심사의 분리(Separation of Concerns) : 관심이 같은 것끼리는 하나의 객체 안으로 또는 친한 객체로 모이게 하고, 관심이 다른 것은 가능한 한 따로 떨어져서 서로 영향을 주지 않도록 분리하는 것

1.2.2 커넥션 만들기의 추출

UserDao의 관심사항

첫째는 DB와 연결을 위한 커넥션을 어떻게 가져올까라는 관심이다. 더 세분화해서 어떤 DB를 쓰고, 어떤 드라이버를 사용할 것이고, 어떤 로그인 정보를 쓰는데, 그 커넥션을 생성하는 방법은 또 어떤 것이다라는 것까지 구분해서 볼 수도 있다.

둘째는 사용자 등록을 위해 DB에 보낼 SQL 문장을 담은 Statement를 만들고 실행하는 것이다. 여기서의 관심은 파리미터로 넘어온 사용자 정보를 Statement에 바인딩 시키고, Statement에 담긴 SQL을 DB를 통해 실행시키는 방법이다.

셋째는 작업이 끝나면 사용한 리소스인 Statement와 Connection 오브젝트를 닫아줘서 소중한 공유 리소스를 시스템에 돌려주는 것이다.

중복 코드의 메서드 추출

똑같은 코드를 2번이상 사용할 경우 메서드로 추출하는 것을 고려해 본다.

변경사항에 대한 검증 : 리팩토링과 테스트

리팩토링 : 기존의 코드를 외부의 동작방식에는 변화 없이 내부 구조를 변경해서 재구성하는 작업 또는 기술을 말한다.

1.2.3 DB 커넥션 만들기의 독립

UserDao 소스코드를 N사와 D사에 제공해주지 않고도 고객 스스로 원하는 DB 커넥션 생성 방식을 적용해 가면서 UserDao를 사용하게 할 수 있을까?

상속을 통한 확장

기존 UserDao 코드를 한 단계 더 분리하면 된다. UserDao에서 메서드의 구현 코드를 제거하고 getConnection을 추상 메서드로 만들어 놓는다. UserDao를 구입한 포털사들은 UserDao클래스를 상속해서 각각의 서브 클래스를 만든다. 이렇게 슈퍼클래스에 기본적인 로직의 흐름을 만들고, 그 기능의 일부를 추상 메서드나 오버라이딩이 가능한 protected 메서드 등으로 만든 뒤 서브 클래스에서 이런 메서드를 필요에 맞게 구현해서 사용하도록 하는 방법을 디자인 패턴에서 템플릿 메서드 패턴이라고 한다. 하지만 이 방법은 상속을 사용했다는 단점이 있다. 다중상속 문제가 걸릴 수 있으며 상속을 통한 상하위 클래스의 관계는 생각보다 밀접하다. 확장된 기능인 DB 커넥션을 생성하는 코드를 다른 DAO 클래스에 적용할 수 없다는 것도 큰 단점이다.

1.3 DAO의 확장

1.3.1 클래스의 분리

이번에는 상속관계가 아닌 완전히 독립적인 클래스로 만들어 보자

1.3.2 인터페이스의 도입

추상화란 어떤 것들의 공통적인 성격을 뽑아내어 이를 따로 분리해내는 작업이다. 인터페이스는 어떤 일을 하겠다는 기능만 정의해놓은 것이다.

1.3.3 관계설정 책임의 분리

UserDao의 클라이언트에서 UserDao를 사용하기 전에, 먼저 UserDao가 어떤 ConnectionMaker의 구현 클래스를 사용할지를 결정하도록 만들어보자.

1.3.4 원칙과 패턴

개방 폐쇄 원칙

클래스나 모듈은 확장에는 열려 있어야 하고 변경에는 닫혀 있어야 한다.

높은 응집도와 낮은 결합도

전략 패턴

자신의 기능 맥락에서 필요에 따라 변경이 필요한 알고리즘을 인터페이스를 통해 통째로 외부로 분리시키고, 이를 구현한 구체적인 알고리즘 클래스를 필요에 따라 바꿔서 사용할 수 있게 하는 디자인 패턴

1.4 제어의 역전(IoC)

1.4.1 오브젝트 팩토리

팩토리

설계도로서의 팩토리

1.4.2 오브젝트 팩토리의 활용

1.4.3 제어권의 이전을 통한 제어관계 역전

1.5 스프링의 IoC

1.5.1 오브젝트 팩토리를 이용한 스프링 IoC

어플리케이션 컨텍스트와 설정정보

스프링에서의 빈 : 스프링이 제어권을 가지고 직접 만들고 관계를 부여하는 오브젝트

스프링 빈 : 스프링 컨테이너가 생성과 관계설정, 사용 등을 제어해주는 제어의 역전이 적용된 오브젝트

빈 팩토리 : 빈의 생성과 관계설정 같은 제어를 담당하는 IoC 오브젝트

어플리케이션 컨텍스트 : IoC 방식을 따라 만들어진 일종의 빈 팩토리, 별도의 정보를 참고해서 빈의 생성, 관계설정 등의 제어 작업을 총괄한다.

DaoFactory를 사용하는 애플리케이션 컨텍스트

DaoFactory를 스프링의 빈 팩토리가 사용할 수있는 본격적인 설정정보로 만들어 보자. 먼저 스프링이 빈 팩토리를 위한 오브젝트 설정을 담당하는 클래스라고 인식할 수 있도록 @Configuration이라는 애노테이션을 추가한다. 또한 오브젝트를 만들어주는 메서드에는 @Bean이라는 애노테이션을 붙여준다.

이제 DaoFactory를 설정정보로 사용하는 애플리케이션 컨텍스트를 만들어보자. 애플리케이션 컨텍스트는 ApplicationContext 타입의 오브젝트다. ApplicationContext를 구현한 클래스는 여러 가지가 있는데 Dao처럼 @Configuration이 붙은 자바 코드를 설정정보로 사용하려면 AnnotationConfigApplicationContext를 이용하면 된다. 애플리케이션 컨텍스트를 만들 때 생성자 파라미터로 DaoFactory 클래스를 넣어준다. 이제 이렇게 준비된 ApplicationContext의 getBean()이라는 메서드를 이용해 UserDao의 오브젝트를 가져올 수 있다.

2010

1

(1) Maintenance is defined as modification of a software product after delivery to correct faults to improve performance, or to adapt the product to a modified environment. Maintenance is considered to be the most costing part of the software life cycle

(2) Inheritance is the software feature to be able to reuse the existing code instead of creating new code when moving software from one environment (platform) to another.

(3) Structured programming involves the splitting of complex program tasks into smaller pieces with clear flow-control and interfaces between components

(4) The advantage of using data encapsulation comes when the implementation of the class changes but the interface remains the same

(5) Assertion contains a boolean expression that you believe will be true when the assertion executes. If it is not true, the system will throw an error. By verifying that the boolean expression is indeed true, the assertion confirms your assumptions about the behavior of your program, increasing your confidence that the program is free of errors.

Experience has shown that writing assertions while programming is one of the quickest and most effective ways to detect and correct bugs.

(6) A good software design recognizes the inevitability of changes and plans an accommodation for them from the very beginning

(7) If you need to write a copy constructor, you also need to write a destructor and operator=

it's because you need something like a deep copy, or some other management of resources. Thus is is almost certain that you will need a destructor and override the assignment operator.